Guide to the Julius Hemphill Papers MSS.542
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Out of Regular, 1992-1995; cuid20532 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Holograph score for two alto saxophones, guitar, cello, and drums. Titled "Out, The Regular" on the album Diminutive Mysteries (1992).
- Painter, The, 1972-1995; cuid20533 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Professionally copied cello part, possibly from 1972 recording session for Dogon A.D. Photocopy of holograph cello part, on page including "Rites" and part of "The Hard Blues." See "Aggregated Parts" for original.
- Parchment, 1989-1995; cuid20534 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Holograph score in pencil and red pen for solo piano. Composed for pianist Ursula Oppens. Personal note from Hemphill to Oppens on obverse of first page.
- Pensive, 1976-1995; cuid20535 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Photocopy of holograph parts for tenor saxophone and trumpet (original is in "Aggregated Parts"). Composition recorded as quintet with saxophone, guitar, cello, drums, and percussion on the Wildflower sessions in 1976. Also recorded as a duo with saxophone and cello on the album Live In New York (1978).
- Pigskin, 1984-1995; cuid20536 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Holograph score for alto saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums. Folder includes holograph guitar part. This composition was incorporated into the "Drunk on God" suite for big band, with the title "Motion as the (Terrible) Language of the Future." See "Drunk on God" for big-band score version.
- Pillars Latino, 1980-1995; cuid20537 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone).
- Plain Song, 1980-1995; cuid20538 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Holograph parts for cello, bass, and guitar, and photocopy of trumpet part from Trumpet Notebook. Folder also contains holograph parts for baritone saxophone and tenor saxophone, from the version for saxophone quartet recorded on the album World Saxophone Quartet (1980). There are several photocopies of a single holograph page, which includes a single line with riffs or chord voicings, perhaps a "background" part for the saxophone quartet version.
- Plateau, 1977-1995; cuid20539 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Holograph part for alto saxophone and photocopies of holograph parts for cello/bass and French horn. This piece was recorded as a trio for alto saxophone, cello, and percussion on Raw Materials and Residuals (1977).
- Pull It, 1968-1995; cuid20540 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Holograph score for soprano saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums. Folder includes professionally copied parts for saxophone, bass, and drums. Instructions for guitar on the score were likely added later.
- Pulsating Shadows, 1968-1995; cuid20541 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Photocopy of holograph score for soprano saxophone and bass.
- R and B, 1978-1995; cuid20542 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone), and photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook. This piece was also used in "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera" in arrangement for saxophone sextet.
- Rapsody, 1968-1995; cuid20543 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Photocopy of holograph part for cello (see "Aggregated Parts" for original).
- Reflective, 1968-1995; cuid20544 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Photocopy of manuscript part in unknown hand for solo flute (See "Aggregated Parts" for original). The part containing this piece also includes the compositions "Trills" and "Hummer."
- Repository, 1968-1995; cuid20545 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Holograph score for soprano saxophone, trumpet, tenor saxophone, French horn, guitar, bass, and percussion.
- Revue, 1980-1995; cuid20546 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). This piece was also used in "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land," arranged for saxophone sextet.
- Rites, 1972-1988; cuid20547 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  Holograph score for soprano saxophone, trumpet, French horn, baritone saxophone, two guitars, bass, and drums. Holograph score for big-band arrangement (five saxophones, two trumpets, two French horns, two trombones, two guitars, bass, and drums). Big-band arrangement likely made for a recording session for Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988) though not included on album. Photocopy of holograph score from Kawaida Notebook for alto saxophone, trumpet, guitar, and bass, with title "Original Rites." Folder includes complete set of professionally copied parts for big-band arrangement, as well as a variety of other parts, holograph, photocopy, and in unknown hands, for trumpet, guitar, cello, bass, drums, and string instruments.
- Rivers of Fire, 1980-1980; cuid20548 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Photocopy of holograph score for soprano saxophone, trumpet, marimba, and cello. This work apparently part of a suite including "Volunteered Blues" and "Hand Packed."
- River Waltz, 1968-1995; cuid20549 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Holograph part for bass, containing thirty measures of chord progressions. Sheet includes a separate composition, "S464Z."
- Romance in Time, 1977-1987; cuid20550 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Folder includes professionally copied parts with annotations in Hemphill's hand in red ink.
- S*, 1978-1978; cuid20551 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for two alto saxophones, included on the album Buster Bee (1978). Folder also includes holograph parts for small-ensemble version for alto saxophone, trumpet, cello, guitar, and bass, and professionally copied parts for guitar and bass. See "Lady S" for big-band arrangement.
- S464Z, 1968-1995; cuid20552 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Photocopy of holograph part for bass, containing sixteen measures of chord progressions. Sheet includes a separate composition, "River Waltz."
- Sanctified Dreams, 1970-1974; cuid20553 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Chiaroscuro Notebook for trumpet and alto saxophone, with empty staves labeled for piano, bass, and drums. Folder includes professionally copied parts for trumpet and alto saxophone, and a photocopy of a part for cello (original is in "Aggregated Parts.")
- Savannah Suite, 1968-1995; cuid20554 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  Several photocopies of holograph score for flute, cello, and drums, with title "Savanah [sic] Suite." Folder includes photocopy of cello part (original in "Aggregated Parts") with title "S. Suite, Motional III."
- Scatterbrain, 1970-1980; cuid20555 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for trio (soprano or alto saxophone, bass or cello, and drums). Folder includes photocopies of holograph parts for soprano saxophone, trumpet, and cello (originals in "Aggregated Parts").
- Serial Abstractions, 1993-1993; cuid20556 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  Holograph score for soprano and baritone saxophones, guitar, cello, and drums.
- Seven, 1968-1995; cuid20557 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Holograph parts for alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. Additional page includes chord chart not in Hemphill's hand.
- Shadows/Echos, 1972-1974; cuid20558 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Kawaida Notebook for flute, trumpet, vibraphone, and drums.
- Short Circuit, 1976-1977; cuid20559 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Photocopy of holograph part for bass (see "Aggregated Parts" for original). The part on which this piece is found contains three other compositions that appear on the album Raw Materials and Residuals (1977).
- Sir Preacher, 1978-1980; cuid20560 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Professionally copied parts for tenor saxophone, flugelhorn, cello, and marimba. This piece may have originally appeared as part of "Sketch #3," one of the movements of "Ralph Ellison's Long Tongue." See "Ralph Ellison's Long Tongue." Folder includes photocopy of holograph score for same instrumentation.
- Sixteen, 1991-1995; cuid20561 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Photocopy of holograph score for alto saxophone, cello, and bass. See "Fifteen" for the original. This piece appears on the same score under the titles "Fifteen" and "One Groove."
- Sixty/Sixty, 1968-1995; cuid20562 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Holograph score for alto saxophone, guitar, and bass and holograph score for soprano saxophone, trumpet, and tenor saxophone. Folder also includes several professionally copied parts—apparently the work of different copyists—for alto saxophone, bass, and drums.
- Slang, 1968-1975; cuid20563 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Photocopy of holograph part for cello (original in "Aggregated Parts"). Largely a graphic score.
- Slices of Light, 1970-1980; cuid20564 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  Holograph score for alto saxophone, trumpet, cello, and percussion. Professionally copied parts for alto saxophone, trumpet, and cello, with part for guitar by a different copyist.
- Slide, 1980-1980; cuid20565 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone).
- Smooth, 1968-1995; cuid20566 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Holograph part for cello. There is an untitled composition, also for cello, on the same sheet.
- Soft Lines, 1968-1995; cuid20567 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for flute, flugelhorn, and cello. Folder includes photocopies of holograph parts (originals in "Aggregated Parts") for cello, flugelhorn, and bass, as well as photocopy of holograph flute part.
- Sounds in the Fog, 1993-1993; cuid20568 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Spiritual Chairs, 1990-1995; cuid20569 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  Photocopies of printed parts for alto saxophone and baritone saxopone, with additional part for baritone in unknown hand, based on material from the final part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land" (see for additional scores and parts).
- Steppin', 1978-1981; cuid20570 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Holograph parts for flute, alto flute, and bass clarinet of a piece composed for the World Saxophone Quartet.
- Stick, 1981-1981; cuid20571 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Professionally copied parts for two alto saxophones and tenor saxophone from a piece composed for the World Saxophone Quartet.
- Strickly Speaking, 1968-1995; cuid20572 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  Photocopy from Musik Hug Notebook of holograph score for guitar and saxophone.
- Sweet D, 1968-1995; cuid20573 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for trumpet, alto saxophone, piano, bass, and drums. Professionally copied parts for alto saxophone and trumpet. Folder includes holograph parts for tenor and baritone saxophone, which, with the trumpet and alto saxophone parts, were used for a version for saxophone quartet(soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). There is a photocopy of a holograph short score with the saxophone quartet instrumentation. Folder includes holograph part for guitar, photocopy of holograph part for cello, and a set of professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet arrangement. "Sweet D" was incorporated into the large-scale piece "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Sweet Lucy, 1968-1995; cuid20574 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  Holograph score for two flutes or oboe, two clarinets, two violins, viola, cello, bass, and voice, including lyrics. Folder includes set of holograph parts, complete except for a change in instrumentation (four cellos instead of two violin, viola, and cello). Also a complete set, in same instrumentation as score, copied in an unknown hand.
- Swirl, 1975-1986; cuid20575 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet (three tenor and baritone).
- Syntax, 1968-1995; cuid20576 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  Photocopy of holograph part for cello (original in "Aggregated Parts"), with fingerings likely in Abdul Wadud's hand.
- Take the A Train, 1986-1995; cuid20577 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone) of arrangement by Hemphill of Billy Strayhorn composition. The parts include instructions for arranging the piece for saxophone sextet. The piece also appears in the score for "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Tendrils, 1991-1991; cuid20578 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Holograph score and parts for saxophone sextet using mixed woodwinds (three flutes, alto saxophone, and two tenor saxophones).
- Testament #5, 1984-1991; cuid20579 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Holograph score for alto saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums. Folder includes two sets of professionally copied parts. The first set, on paper and paper vellum, is for alto saxophone, bass, and drums, with notes to the copyist in Hemphill's hand. The second set of parts includes a guitar part in addition to alto saxophone, bass, and drums.
- Three-Step, 1990-1995; cuid20580 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet (two soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone). The second tenor part is photocopied. See "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land: III" for additional scores and parts.
- Tightenin, 1968-1995; cuid20581 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  Photocopy of holograph part for cello (original in "Aggregated Parts").
- Touchic', 1981-1995; cuid20582 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). Folder includes complete set of professionally copied parts.
- Trills, 1968-1995; cuid20583 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  Photocopy of holograph score for solo soprano saxophone (see "Aggregated Parts" for original). Appears on score with compositions "Hummer" and "Reflective."
- Twilight, 1986-1995; cuid20584 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  Holograph score for four flutes, soprano saxophone, and tenor saxophone.
- Unknown, The, 1993-1993; cuid20585 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Holograph score for alto and baritone saxophones, guitar, cello, and drums.
- Very So, 1984-1987; cuid20586 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  Holograph score for soprano saxophone, two guitars, bass, drums, and percussion. Likely written for the JAH Band.
- Void, 1979-1995; cuid20587 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Musik Hug Notebook for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Although the score is untitled, professionally copied parts, also in folder, bear the title "Void."
- Volunteered Blues, 1980-1980; cuid20588 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  Holograph score and professionally copied parts for alto saxophone, trumpet, cello, and percussion.
- What I Know Now, 1980-1995; cuid20589 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  Folder includes several versions of this piece for different instrumentation. Holograph score and professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Holograph score, with two photocopies, for big band (alto saxophone, four flutes, flugelhorn, French horn, baritone horn, tuba, vibraphone, and bass). Folder includes professionally copied parts for bass and drums, a holograph piano part with instructions for performance, and parts for flute, two violins, cello, and soprano saxophone, in an unknown hand. See "Plan B" for orchestral arrangement by Christopher Bankey.
- What I Know Now - Big Band Parts, 1980-1980; cuid20590 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  Professionally copied parts for big band (alto saxophone, flour flutes, flugelhorn, French horn, baritone horn, tuba, vibraphone, and bass).
- Will's Words, 1968-1995; cuid20591 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  Photocopy of holograph part for unidentified B-flat instrument (original in "Aggregated Parts.")
- Wind/Rhythms, 1981-1981; cuid20592 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (switching among soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone, and flute, alto flute, and bass clarinet) with notes for percussion. Suite with five movements: "Fixation," "Flair," "Ji-Ji Tune," "Another Feeling," and "Stick." See "Stick" and "Ji-Ji Tune" for additional parts. Composition written for collaboration with Max Roach and M'Boom. Folder includes two pages with instructions for performance.
- Would Boogie, 1970-1980; cuid20593 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  Holograph parts for trumpet, alto saxophone, guitar, and bass, some titled "Wood Boogie."
- Zuli, 1968-1995; cuid20594 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  Holograph parts for trumpet, tenor saxophone, and cello. Photocopy of holograph score for three unidentified instruments.
- Aggregated Parts, 1968-1995; cuid20595 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  Parts for multiple compositions, with more than one composition per sheet, in a variety of hands though many in holograph.
- Untitled Scores and Parts, 1968-1995; cuid20596 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Parts and scores, many in holograph, with unidentified or fragmentary compositions. Outside of folder includes notes in Marty Ehrlich's hand.
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land: I. The Cabin, 1990-1995; cuid20597 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Holograph score for "The Cabin," the first part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land." This large-scale composition was written for saxophone sextet, with extensive switching by each player. Individual movements include "Cabin Opener"; "Harry"; "Liza - Tearful Farewell"; "George"; "Slave Dance"; "Chloe"; "Tom"; "Men's Chase / Haley's Dance"; "Tom's Goodbye"; "Boat Music"; "Slave's Walk"; "Lucy"; "St. Clair Family"; "Eva and Tom"; "Dixie Dance"; "Death of Eva"; "Auction"; "Tom's Whipping"; "Ghosts"; "Retrograde"; "Fanfare for Lincoln."
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land: II. Eliza on the Ice, 1990-1995; cuid20598 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Holograph score for "Eliza on the Ice," the second part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land." This large-scale composition was written for saxophone sextet, with extensive switching by each player. Individual movements include "Knee Play"; "Eliza on the Ice"; "Aint' I a Woman"; "Elevator Music"; "Betsy"; "Prayer Music"; "End of Betsy"; "Fanfare for Maya"; "Soft Shoe"; "Maya"; "Prayer Music."
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land: III. The Promised Land, 1990-1995; cuid20599 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Holograph score for "The Promised Land," the third part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land." This large-scale composition was written for saxophone sextet, with extensive switching by each player. Individual movements include "At Dr. King's Table"; "Step Dance"; "Dixie Dance"; "Football"; "Ascension"; "Crossformation"; "Opening (Hymn)"; "Three-Step."
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land: IV. The Last Supper, 1990-1995; cuid20600 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Holograph score for "The Last Supper," the fourth part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land." This large-scale composition was written for saxophone sextet, with extensive switching by each player. Individual movements include "Arthur"; "Trans"; "Men's Trio"; "Ringmere"; "Ringmere Canon"; "Four Saints"; "Spiritual Chairs"; "Lenny"; "The Children's Song."
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land - Assorted Parts, 1990-1995; cuid20601 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Various parts for saxophone sextet for the different movements of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land. Many in pencil, in different hands. Some parts include cut-out photocopies of scores, assembled into performance order. Several parts identify the name of the musician in the original performance.
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land - Photocopy scores, 1990-1995; cuid20602 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  Various photocopies of scores for "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land - Part Notebooks, 1990-1995 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
- Drunk on God, 1988-1995; cuid20603 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  Holograph score of "Drunk on God" suite for big band (five saxophones, two trumpets, two French horns, two trombones, two guitars, drums, and bass), written for the album Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988). The movements (titled differently on the recording) are "Nago: Testament"; "Maliaka: Drum/Woman"; "Pigskin" or "Motion as the Lang"; "Float"; "Bob Scene: KC Line"; "Anchorman"; "From Out of Nowhere: The Big Drum Speaks." Several movements exist as independent compositions.
- Drunk on God - Parts I, 1988-1995; cuid20604 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  Set of professionally copied parts for several movements of the "Drunk on God" suite ("Nago: Testament," "Maliaka: Drum/Woman," "Motion as the Lang"/"Pigskin," and "Float"). Includes annotations in various hands.
- Drunk on God - Parts II, 1988-1995; cuid20605 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  Set of professionally copied parts for several movements of the "Drunk on God" suite ("Anchorman," "The Big Drum Speaks," and "Bob Scene - KC Line."). Includes annotations in various hands.
- Ralph Ellison's Long Tongue, 1978-1995; cuid20606 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  Holograph score with multiple movements from the theatrical work "Ralph Ellison's Long Tongue." Instrumentation includes alto and tenor saxophone, trumpet, French horn, and cello. Individual movements are "Sketch 1," "Sketch 2," Sketch 3," "Sketch 4," and "Sir Preacher." Folder includes holograph parts for two additional movements: "Carnival Barker," for which there is an alto saxophone part, and "Orator," for which there are parts for trumpet, cello, and soprano saxophone. These parts include settings of text based on the novel by Ralph Ellison, Invisible Man (1952).
- Water Music for Woodwinds - Parts, 1976-1995; cuid20607 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  Professionally copied parts for seven instrumentalists playing various woodwinds. The parts are identified by the names of the original musicians, with annotations in various hands and photocopied parts attached with tape.
- Water Music for Woodwinds - Materials for Edition, 1976-2003; cuid20608 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  Photocopies of the professionally copied parts for seven woodwind players, with further annotations in red ink. Folder includes two printouts of computer-engraved full score, with annotations in red pencil and ink by Marty Ehrlich, dated January 2003. Additional pages contain photocopies of hand-written notes on performance sequence.
- Plan B - Working Materials, 1993-1995; cuid20609 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  Manuscript scores, likely in Christopher Bankey's hand, for an arrangement for orchestra of several Hemphill compositions. Includes several pages of short score, with notes on instrumentation, as well as two pagse of full score with measure numbers and notes for insertion. The individual movements of "Plan B" are "Border Town," "What I Know Now," and "Dogon A.D."
- Plan B - Printed Score, 1993-1995; cuid20610 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  Printout of computer-engraved full score for "Plan B," an arrangement for orchestra by Christopher Bankey of three Hemphill compositions, "Border Town," "What I Know Now," and "Dogon A.D." The score is printed as two pages per 11"x17" sheet, fifty-three sheets in total.
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - Sextet Parts, 1985-1990; cuid20611 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  Professionally copied parts for the saxophone sextet contained in "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera."
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - String Parts, 1985-1990; cuid20612 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Professionally copied parts for two violins, two violas, and two cellos for "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera."
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - Winds/Brass Parts, 1985-1990; cuid20613 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Professionally copied parts for piccolo, two trumpets, two trombones, and French horn, for "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera."
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - Rhythm Section Parts, 1985-1990; cuid20614 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Professionally copied parts for piano, bass, drumset, and percussion, for "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera."
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - Photocopy of Holograph score, 1985-1990; cuid20615 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  Photocopy of holograph score for "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera," as well as performance instructions on loose sheets in various hands.
- Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera - Assorted photocopies of score, 1985-1990; cuid20616 (Box 16, Folder 2)